[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at
se-radio.net sc radio is brought to you
by the ieee computer society by ieee
software magazine
online at computer.org software
developers are you ready it's time to
upgrade your data platform to inner
systems iris choose your language
choose your tools choose your
environment collaborate build faster and
deploy more efficiently
when you can make faster decisions
there's no telling what you'll create
ready set code start coding for free
visit intersystems.com try to try iris
hello everyone welcome to software
engineering radio
today we welcome ryan ripley to our show
ryan is a professional scrum trainer and
host of the podcast agile for humans
in the past ryan has worked as a
software developer
in engineering management as a scrum
master at many companies
ryan also has a new book fixing your
scrum practical solutions to common
scrum problems
welcome to the show ryan is there
anything in your bio that you'd like to
add
no that was that's really nicer than
what i deserve so thank you so much and
uh thanks for having me on the show
before we start i'd like to call out
some related episodes
there has been a recent episode that
contrasts
agile with waterfall episode 401
and there are also some older episodes
episodes
60 161 170 and 181
we'll have link in the show notes while
these were recorded several years ago
i believe there's still excellent
introductions to scrum
its roles and artifacts and some best
practices
so today we don't plan to cover the
basics of scrum
instead we want to focus on
anti-patterns that
dull the impact of scrum with that
let me ask you ryan why do organizations
want to adopt scrum i actually don't
think scrum's the
the goal um it's interesting i think
organizations are trying to figure out
how do we how do we build the right
thing at the right time for the right
customer
and so they're after delivery they're
after customer satisfaction they're
after
consistency they're after all these
great things
and the current methods don't work you
know trying to pick big dates out
in the future and land to those targets
and
negotiating all those big upfront design
projects they haven't traditionally hit
those
those really important targets that i
just mentioned and so companies are
turning to empiricism
right so they're learning by doing right
empirical process control means that
we take observed behaviors observed
outcomes
and we inspect what's going on through
transparent work and we make
adaptations frequently as we go and so
right now
scrum is the only framework out there
that at least i'm aware of
that that allows us to actually do that
and so when when people say why would
companies want scrum my unusual answer
is they don't they want to be able to
deliver something that people want
and right now scrum is what's empowering
companies to do that
that makes sense so i'm wondering though
why does the scrum guide call scrum as
difficult to master you know it's
interesting scrum is
i liken it to the game of chess right so
chess has
very simple rules and you can learn the
rules in an afternoon
and it takes people years or even a
lifetime to to hit a grandmaster
high level i think the same is true with
scrum you can read that it's a 17 pages
you could read it in one sitting you
could start doing some of the
the events and start working with some
of the artifacts and the roles very
quickly
but what we find out is the second you
start using scrum impediments occur
and the ways that your current that your
organization currently works
wow we run into some friction and so it
takes a very long time to learn how to
leverage agility how to leverage
empiricism how to leverage scrum in a
way that
that's actually an advantage for your
company early on
it's very disruptive and so it takes
years and years and years like these
ideas that
you know you'll see in our industry you
know six months we'll do an agile
transformation and everything will be
perfect
run away from that like that snake oil
that's that's nonsense
it takes many many years of of practice
of work of application uh in order to
to get an organization truly working in
in a great way
with scrum with kanban with any of these
agile methods
and so yes very simple rules very small
scrum guide very quick to read
but it takes years to unravel
organizational dysfunction it takes
years to change
mindsets from you know command and
control to servant leadership it takes
years to really get these lessons
learned and to change the dna of a
company so yes scrum is very simple
to learn but it takes years and years
and years to master because of all of
those
other things happening around us what
are some of the prereqs though that an
organization should have before they
even start
you know i'm not sure if there's a
prerequisite right i think that
any organization developing products
could adopt scrum
you know i i think deciding you know
what i should change that
a pro a good prerequisite the leadership
team is on board with the shifts in
mindset
and with the changes in the way we're
trying to work right if leadership is on
board i think that leads to
a high a much higher potential for
success
but as far as any other prereq we just
need to get started right that's
what gets me is so many organizations
try to use waterfall to implement agile
they call in a big box company
with a with a three-letter acronym for
its name and they say
give us the two-year plan to adopt agile
and they lay out a two-year road map and
they give them the playbook and all
these other things that are anti-agile
that are completely not congruent with
with the principles and values of agile
and try to plan out using waterfall and
agile implementation
sometimes we just need to get started
it's through doing so there's this great
uh
great agilist out there his name is
woody zul has a great twitter feed at
woodysoul
and if you follow it you see a lot of
his agile maximums and and one of them
that i really love is
it is through doing the work that we
that we learn about the work we need to
do
and so sometimes we have to get in dig
into the work
get a little bit done get some feedback
to figure out if what we're doing is
right
and i wish companies would take that
approach instead so prerequisite would
be leadership on board the second would
be
throw out the playbooks and do many many
small experiments
adapt and learn inspect and adapt and
keep going towards continual improvement
and i think those two things
will take companies very very far got it
so
the organization gets started i'm sure
every organization customizes these
processes sure how would you distinguish
between customizing it to meet the needs
of the company
versus doing it completely wrong and you
know still get the essence of scrum
what do you think can be changed and
should not be touched
i leave the framework alone is the
advice i give so the scrum framework has
a lot of air in between
right there's a lot of there's a lot of
space between the events and the
artifacts and the roles
to where companies can do a lot of
things that make sense to them within
their context
the only rule that i often will give is
do not change the framework itself
you know when companies are when they
feel this this desire this need to
change the framework to modify scrum
um in some way it's usually to cover up
some kind of
impediment or some kind of
organizational dysfunction
so rather than change scrum change the
way you're working
right because there's probably something
you're covering up that will bubble up
later
regardless of the change you make today
so i just treat it as it's a scaffolding
it's a framework do a lot of
you can do a lot of smart custom things
within the boundaries of scrum
but please do not change the framework
itself
okay the organization took care advice
they got started
they kept the framework in place now
after some time
how do they know it's working how do
they know that
it's a successful adoption versus
something is wrong
are we able to deliver are we delivering
high quality potentially releasable
products that delight
customers if we're getting to done and
the customers are satisfied right
so if we have roi if we have customer
satisfaction if we're having an
impact on the world all those things are
are great measures
of of making sense of whether or not
you're being successful
but i think first and foremost like i
think there's a lot of different types
of agilis
i i do not fall into the camp of the the
touchy feely
you know drum circle kumbaya type of
agile coach or scrum master i am very
much centered on delivery
so if we cannot ship an increment of
product by the end of a sprint
that is the first sign to me that we are
not being successful
if we have customers who are not
delighted by our products and we have
people who are not willing to pay for
the things that we're building
that's probably another sign that we've
made a mistake but for me first and
foremost an organization's ability to
actually
ship something is where i typically look
first let's talk a little bit of the
evolution of the scrum guide itself
so when were the scrum values added to
the guide
and why and are there any other
significant additions that have been
made over the years
you know i'm trying to remember which
exact revision the scrum values came
back
and i it was either it might have been
the 2011 change
and i i think that was significant it's
interesting in the original
there's the the black covered book where
uh that ken schwaber and mike beadle
co-authored
and the values are in that book so the
values have been with scrum for a very
long time and for some reason they were
they missed
putting the the values in a few versions
of the scrum guide thankfully they
brought them back
and that was i think that's one of the
biggest changes uh to the guide simply
because it's very easy
to turn scrum into a process right keep
in mind it's a framework it's not a
process
and so people will try to take a very
legalistic viewpoint of scrum they'll
try to turn it into
you know steps 1 through 100 to product
delivery nirvana
they'll do all these crazy things like
i've seen i've seen companies and
organizations where
here's our 350 page playbook on how to
do scrum here
that's totally antithetical to to the
philosophy
and the principles behind scrum itself
instead the values came back
and they gave us some insights into yes
the the events and the artifacts and the
roles are important
but this is a human practice and so
behavior is paramount
right people people and culture will
crush
a scrum implementation faster than
anything else and so these values of
focus
openness commit commitment courage and
respect
they really teach us that culture is
is really important and the fact that
that these that these
values exist and can help us are really
important it's why i talk about
leadership going first you know if the
leadership team
does not believe in focus which means
doing fewer things at once but getting
things to
done there's a problem if they don't
believe that openness is important
right openness to new ideas openness to
being wrong
openness to um support diversity
inclusion all these things
that we're going to have a problem if
commitment
is misunderstood you know far too often
commitment is is interpreted as
commitment to scope which we never
commit to in scrum we
never commit to scope we commit to
bringing our best selves forward we
commit to being a positive teammate we
commit to a sprint goal
commitment is is all over the framework
but never to scope and that's one of the
big misunderstandings
courage is essential it's going to take
courage to tell a stakeholder no
it's going to take courage to tell a
customer not yet it's going to take
courage to speak truth to power
and if we can't do that our scrum
practice will be flawed and respect
think about all the challenging
difficult things i just listed
if we can't do those things respectfully
this all falls apart
and so these behaviors came back and
really made a significant shift in the
way that the people and organizations
view scrum
hopefully for the better you know i
think that you know as you noted was a
major change
and i think it's one of the most
significant they've done in a very long
time
so it's either in your book or in an
email from you
that you said you don't believe in
scaling scrum i'd like to understand
that a little bit
yeah the scrum guide does say that the
strength of an individual team
can be expanded to networks of teams but
i'm confused by your statement could you
elaborate
you know i've yet to run into a company
where scaling was appropriate
you know i think you know very large
companies especially they jump straight
into scaling they'll they'll go do
safe they'll do nexus they'll do less
they'll do dad they'll do
whichever flavor of scaling they've
they've picked out
but without ever actually having a
single successful scrum team off the
ground
and running right and so to me it's
it's it's an extreme statement and it
definitely gets attention but i really
mean it where
i've yet to see where scaling made sense
let's get amazing at scrum let's
actually
have some scrum teams stood up we you
can have four or five scrum teams up
without scale
without the scaling frameworks in place
and really learn
how to make scrum work as a competitive
advantage for your organization and
really work hard to
get the impediments out of the way and
to make the cultural changes necessary
and to change the way that the
organization is struck
get all that stuff figured out and when
you've done that
then start thinking about how do we
scale this out to you know a hundred a
thousand how many people we have but
but let's get good at scrum first and
really that's
that's at the center of that comment
that i made let's talk about
roles a little bit and i'd like to start
with the rule of engineering management
like you said getting engineering
leadership buying or
just leadership buying is important so
why is the role of engineering
management missing from the scrum guy
you know the the development team is a
self-organizing
cross-functional group of people who are
capable of delivering product
right and so in that sense
engineering managers can make a great
impact in clearing impediments they can
make a great impact in taking care of
the hr functions
but we're not looking to outside people
telling a dev team how to do their work
anymore you know when we empower a dev
team to decide how best to do their work
we're telling those
nine ten individuals how many other
people are on the on the dev team
look we've we trust you to be across a
self-organized or organizing
cross-functional team you're going to
figure out how best to do your work
we're going to hold you accountable
to getting to done we're going to hold
you accountable to delivery
but you get to decide how to get there
with some constraints
along the way and so from a from a scrum
perspective whether you have an
engineering manager
a people manager you know a lead
architect
whatever structures and boundaries you
put in place outside of the scrum
team that's up to your organization
right it's a framework
but when we have that dev team in place
these are empowered people
and they are cross-functional and they
are capable of delivering an increment
and if they're not
maybe we can lean on that engineering
manager or that that architect or
whoever it is to help
does that make sense yeah that makes a
lot of sense and that
brings me to the scrum master because he
seems pretty key in this
what experience must a scrum master have
yeah it's an interesting question i've
i've met scrum masters who
came from a business analyst background
i've met scrum masters who have been
developers
i came from a development background and
and then went into
some project management and then a scrum
master role
i've seen people decide that you know
leadership wasn't there
you know being on a a director a vp you
know whichever level they were at
that didn't work for them and they
became a scrum master so i i'm not sure
experience is critical and as far as
like in
any one area i've actually seen where
scrum masters who were previously
developers caused a lot of harm you know
they thought they knew best they started
giving direction to a dev team they
started kind of interfering with some of
the boundaries of the roles and
and so we have to be really careful how
some of that plays out
i think there are some important things
though that can help you know when i'm
when i'm thinking
about who could be a scrum master or
what are we looking for
you know there's three things that
really come to mind it's this person
that's going to fill a scrum master role
they have to love their team
and it's a weird word to use in tech and
in product right
but what we really mean is they have a
deep care for the people that they're
serving
and that we have to have this feeling in
place because the second thing is
this person this scrum master has to
want every member on this team
and the collective team to be as wildly
successful
as possible and so as a scrum master i'm
helping people get promoted
i'm trying to get people elevated in
their careers i'm trying to help them
get leveled up i'm putting their
career advancement ahead of my own right
i am literally serving them to
to get them to higher levels of of
success and achievement
and the final thing that i really have
to have wired in my head
is that i have zero tolerance for
organizational impediments
i refuse to let something in the
organization sit idle that's
keeping my team from develop from
delivering right i have
zero tolerance for the things holding us
back and so do i have to go and tactif
and tactfully work with people to solve
those absolutely
but i do not let those things sit and so
if i if i
if i truly love the team i want them to
be wildly successful
and i have zero tolerance for the things
that are getting in the way
that's what i'm looking for because i
can teach the framework i hope i can
that's how i make a living these days
right so i'm
i'm a professional scrum trainer with
scrum.org i hope i can teach the
framework
but what i cannot do is put those three
things into someone's brain
so whether they come from a project
management background a development
background a leadership background
you know i've even seen people who have
come from an educational like a teaching
background who have stepped into this
role beautifully
as long as they have that mindset that
servant leadership mindset locked in
and that they're serving others and
they're trying to elevate others and no
tolerance for organizational impediments
i think we can teach the rest
okay so i was going to ask you what role
does certification play
so you did talk about the fact that
understanding the framework is
important yep is there anything else
that's uh important about the
certification
you know i what what i love about being
a trainer for scrum dot org is we have
separated the training from the
certification
right if you i think the certification
is a credential
i think it gives people a sense of what
you've worked at
i think it gives people a sense of of an
accomplishment that you've achieved i'll
tell you what if you can pass the psm2
or the psm3 so the professional scrum
master level 2
and three from scrum.org i will
interview you
if i'm hiring you automatically get in a
live interview
right those are tricky assessments
they're very they show a high level of
skill
i think that's meaningful but for me i'm
really looking for experience right so i
think it's impo
it's an important blend i i would
caution people don't put so much
emphasis on the certificate
you know the classes are important too
but it's really the experience and how
much
impact you've had on your scrum teams
that are really the most important right
and so i think it's a balance you know
the certs can can offer some really good
information about people but ultimately
have you had an impact on your scrum
team have you actually helped a team
deliver have you empowered someone to do
something they didn't think they could
do have you removed an
organizational issue that led to a great
thing i think that's the really
important stuff the certs can help along
the way because they can kind of
i've always used certifications myself
as a guidepost for learning
like it gave me a structure and a
boundary something a goal to achieve
i think that's a great way to use them
and uh they certainly have a place
and they're certainly important but man
it's the how we apply that cert how we
apply that learning
are we making people's lives better
that's the really important outcome
in my opinion so the purpose of the
scrum master is to enable the team to
succeed
by removing impediments or any other
ways
so what are the things that scrum
masters should not do what are the
anti-patterns to watch out for
well we wrote a whole book on that
fixing your scrum
practical solutions to common scrum
problems so todd miller and i co-wrote
that book
it's available now amazonpragprog.com
the whole book is full of things that a
scrum master should not do
right i think when we when we take away
the agency of others is where we really
make a huge mistake right
so when we step in and try to fulfill
the product owner's role for them or
when we step in and tell the dev team
what to do
when we step in and neglect or when we
neglect the organization like we don't
go out and talk to leadership we don't
talk to hr we ignore
the mechanisms around the dev team i
think we do the most disservice right
and so don't do that like go out there
and
if you can fulfill your three levels of
service to the product owner to the dev
team into the org
and to do that in a way to where you are
empowering others and not
stepping in and commanding and demanding
i think you'll end up okay but if not
check the book you know there are
definitely a lot of anti-patterns there
and some interesting ways to help you
diagnose and solve those issues
so don't command and don't demand
you know it sounds so simple doesn't it
um but we see so many scrum masters
violate this
you are a servant leader when you're in
a scrum mass role now i'm now
and some people might have an issue with
that i'm not saying you're a doormat
there are times when you have to take
direct action
right there are times when your job is
to uphold scrum or protect the team
or to to do all these great things but
you know what that's not most of the
time
most of the time you're there to help
people discover their own truths for
themselves or to coach them in a way to
where they discover their best answer
that applies to their situation or to go
out and build relationships that clear
impediments that help
others have great success and i and i
think if we're doing that
more often than the times when we step
in and take direct action
are less damaging right so don't be a
doormat you're still in a
powerful influential role but you wield
that power in such a way that you're
you're you're promoting and building
other people up
not commanding and directing them
hopefully that makes sense
yeah i think uh also maybe i just like
to say that the scrum master is the big
bridge
between the team and everybody else
right i think yeah
i think we're a bridge to the outside
org but hopefully that bridge is
constantly shrinking
right i mean the ultimate goal is to
connect people
and to not be a proxy and so ideally
like let's take a sprint review for
example
if we're in a sprint review and a
stakeholder has a question for the dev
team
hopefully your stakeholders are
attending your sprint reviews right
they don't have to go through the scrum
master initially that might make sense
but let's get to where the dev team and
the stakeholders are talking directly
right let's get to a point to where the
scrum master doesn't have to be in the
middle of every conversation because
they've made such a great connection
between people
but yeah initially it's a bridge and
that bridge will hopefully shrink over
time
make sense let's talk now about the
product owner
what is the intent of this role an
example would be great
so a product owner they are there to
maximize the value of the work
that's to be performed by a dev team so
they are watching the dollars in the
cents
all right they're they're they're
protecting the investment being made by
the organization they are there to
define
what winning looks like what value
actually means right so
that we like to say during our scrum.org
courses
that there's three v's of product
ownership
vision value and validation so they're
there to provide the big product vision
of our of our efforts like what is
what's the impact we're trying to have
on the world by by executing on this
project
the second v is value so they're not
only do they set the vision they define
what value actually means
right so how do we know we've put
something good into the world this is
what
what that could mean and then finally
validation they have they're responsible
they're accountable
for checking to see what we delivered
did it actually reach the value we set
out to get
and so yeah that product owner is a very
busy person because not only do they
have their scrum responsibilities
they're also still an agile product
manager
so they're out talking to customers and
they're doing a b testing and they're
doing market research and they're doing
meetings with leadership and management
to discuss budgets and
they've got all of these huge
responsibilities outside of scrum but
then a lot of work with the scrum team
as well
and uh but if i were to sum it up value
is what the product owner is all about
they are there to make sure that what
we're building
is is what people actually want
right and that we're what we're
investing in running a scrum team
that we're going to get a good return on
that does that help
yes it does and i want to talk more
about what you said about the scrum
master
being really busy because that's a lot
of charter
so in your book you say that it's
important to have
one product owner for a product the
scrum guide says that
the product owner is one person not a
committee
in one of our previous episodes 161
there was a concept of a product owner
team that was explored
so from my point of view the goal as i
understand is really to speak with
one voice to the dev team if that's
correct
why be so dogmatic about having it be
one person because it's a lot of work it
could be a huge
product as well yeah so we need
one voice for a product right so i
i did i did not listen to to 161 i'm not
sure what they meant by a product
team in scrum we have one person
whose voice is respected by the entire
organization
who can make decisions tactically
strategically and financially about a
product without waiting without
permission
you know part of the the reason that we
have a single empowered product owner
is that we don't want to wait for
decisions to be made right when we have
a proxy product owner or even a team of
product owners let's say that i'm on a
team of product owners well there's
always
one head product owner regardless of the
team right
and what if i don't have the authority
to make the decision that the that my
scrum team is asking me about
so now i have to go get an answer from
someone else i've become a proxy this
causes delay this also it could cause
it could cause wasted work it could
cause waste in a product especially if i
don't communicate the need correctly to
this head person
and that person makes a decision that
it's just there's so many errors and
and issues that come up in scrum we have
one empowered voice
one empowered person now that doesn't
mean that this the product owner cannot
get help
right so when it comes to product
backlog refinement there's no reason why
the dev team cannot do that for a
product owner there's no reason why
you know some of these activities cannot
be shared amongst the entire scrum team
but what it what it comes down to is
this there is one
person held accountable for the value of
a product
on a scrum team and as long as we get
that the way that you configure it
i'm not i'm not all that worried about
it thanks for that
ryan you talked about the product toner
but i didn't hear you mentioning the
word
backlog is that right yeah why is that
well i mean a product owner expresses
value
through a product backlog they also
express their vision for the product
through a product backlog
right so a product backlog holds all of
the things that we
could do in order to achieve our product
vision
and in order to put value into the world
right
and so the way that a product owner
expresses these things
is through product backlog items which
could be a feature a story
a bug whatever it is that we're going to
work on and they order that product
backlogged by what they value most
and so i just see a product backlog as
an expression of vision and also an
expression of value
so this is the tool that they use this
is the artifact they use
to communicate vision and value with the
dev team and with stakeholders
calling all developers there's no
telling what you can create when you
upgrade your data platform to inner
systems iris
are you ready to build the applications
you want however you want them
are you ready to develop applications
faster than ever collaborate
build faster and deploy more efficiently
tomorrow's next breakthroughs are
waiting for you today
enter systems iris data platform ready
set code start coding for free
visit intersystems.com try to try iris
okay let's segue now to the dev team
with that
you mentioned cross-functional teams
earlier how
critical is that you know what's the
difference between having future teams
and component teams you know what scrum
allows both
and so i i want to get that out of the
way quickly that scrum allows features
teams it allows component teams
when i'm talking about a
cross-functional team though what i mean
is this is a team
who can deliver an increment of product
on their own
they're not dependent on another team to
do something for them
right and this is this is the goal uh
because this kind of team can move
quickly
look we we implement scrum in an
organization to use it as a competitive
advantage
part of that competitive advantage is
time to market being able to
take an idea and get it out into the
world quickly and so just like with our
product owner discussion if we have to
wait for decisions if we have to wait
for permission if we have to wait for
these proxies
we lose time if a dev team has to be
dependent on another team
to get something done we lose more time
right we're giving up this competitive
advantage
by organizing ourselves in bad ways and
so when we say cross-functional this
team can build
and ship a product increment on their
own and when we say
a single empowered product owner what
we're saying is this person can make the
the call so that we're not waiting
because we're
look implementing scrum is a huge
investment it's very expensive to get me
to teach a class it's very expensive to
hire an agile coach it's very expensive
to hire scrum at
look we spend so much money doing this
it must be a competitive advantage to
the organization or else it's a waste
right
and so the things that i'm talking about
self-organizing teams cross-functional
teams empowered product owners
all of these things get us to that to
that
competitive advantage so that the
investment in this scrum adoption is
worth it
does that make sense yeah that makes
sense so my next question was going to
be what
you know creates this high-performing
team is there anything you want to add
to that
besides what you mentioned
cross-functional teams
empowered teams and a single product
owner
you know what i think leaving teams
alone for a while um helps us get to a
high-performing team i think people need
time to learn how
uh each other work and and uh they need
time to
to build relationships and they need
time to get used to how one another is
gonna
to function and work together and learn
the team norms and
and all those great things i think one
of the saddest things that todd and i
kind of talked about in our book you
know far too many companies will go down
this path
of adopting scrum and they'll have this
one pilot team
and they'll get this scrum team together
and usually these teams can do pretty
well right
and so they they start performing and
they start doing great things and over
you know 12 to 18 months whatever the
timeline is
they get to high performance and then
the organization says wow we've got 10
people who understand scrum really well
now so let's break these 10 people up
let's put them into 10 separate teams
and and that's how we're going to grow
agility
and it always makes me really sad
because i look at and i think why would
you ever slaughter a unicorn
like why would you do that if you have
this high performing team
who's taken the time to work together to
gel to
to form and norm and storm and do all
those great things and finally get to
high performance
why would you wreck that right it's such
a rare thing and so i think
time is one of those big ingredients too
give people time to work together give
them time to
to come together as a team you know i i
think when i when i talk about this in
my classes i talk
about uh the dream team so usa
basketball right the first time that
the olympics allowed professional
players in and we sent michael jordan
the greatest basketball player of all
time by the way michael jordan
is the goat we sent him and larry bird
and magic johnson
and patrick ewing and chris mullins and
christian leightoner and
and all these uh john stockton carl
malone
i think barkley was on dream team one i
mean the
elijah won we sent these who sent the
best of the best
and they almost lost their first game
right they didn't know how to play well
together
and they had it took some time and some
practice and some coaching to figure
that out
and i think it's the same with
developers we could have the best
developers on the planet but on day one
they're not going to be great together
it takes that time to actually figure
that out and so i think time is a huge
huge factor
in giving teams the space and time to to
learn how to be high performing together
i think that's really crucial fair
enough however
you know i'm not sure i completely agree
with
not changing a team once at form you
know many things happen
a team member may want to do something
else
some of our previous episode uh did deal
with the concept of travel between teams
where people did want to try different
projects or different technologies
or they were experts in certain areas
that they wanted to seed in other teams
they also dealt with this concept of
guilds where
people from many teams could come
together on a specific topic
so that there's more awareness so i'm
not really sure
what you exactly meant by leaving teams
alone because
you know in practice that may not be
possible
well i think if we're not going to
follow that i think we have to
acknowledge that every time we change
the composition of a team
we are going to have lower performance
for a while and i think if we
if we go into those decisions
understanding that we are causing a team
to perform
at a lower level for a a decent period
of time
uh by switching people in and out then i
think it's a fine decision but we have
to know we're making that trade-off
so let me ask you this scrum recognizes
or doesn't recognize
title for deaf team members regardless
of what they actually do
what happens in practice you know what
is the role of technical leads
you know what that kind of fades away on
a self-organizing team
right i you know a technical lead is a
those people are typically more senior
in their career they're
they're they're usually great
technologists they and they're still
very valuable on a scrum team we just
don't recognize one voice higher than
another
on a scrum team right everyone it's
equals among
it's it's you know it's like the round
table you know king arthur's court right
it's it's equals among many and
yeah so i think those kind of ideas kind
of fade away after a while
and we just become highly collaborative
we respect one another we
we leverage um each other's experiences
we rely on one another we help one
another and we don't worry about
those titles so much right i mean really
the the lead developer kind of titles
it's really tied to compensation
and so if i'm in a scrum master role i'm
going to go to hr and say look by
creating hierarchies in our teams we're
really causing some issues
with self-organization we're causing
some issues with our team culture
is there a different way that we can
compensate people fairly for experience
without creating all of this hierarchy
on a team
and let's sort through that let's
actually address the issue and that's
something a good scrum master will
recognize quickly
and and seek to correct okay switching
gears a little bit
the organization has decided to adopt
scrum
and they decide to do feature teams and
they have
let's say four or five feature teams and
they all contribute towards the end
product
it is important to ensure consistency
between the different
let's say pages or ui pages that are
implemented by these feature teams how
do you do that how do you ensure
consistency between what multiple teams
are doing
yeah so in scrum when we have multiple
teams working on us
on the same product we have to set a
baseline definition of done
and so branding standards ux ui controls
and
all of those things go into a definition
of done
right and so when we have that base
definition of done
the four or five teams all agree to
follow it it's a shared understanding of
what completeness means it's a shared
understanding of what potentially
releasable means
now all of those teams can go back and
make the guideline can make the
definition of done more strict
they can hold themselves to a higher bar
of quality
but what they cannot do is circumvent
the common areas
that all the teams have agreed must be
consistent
and so i i think the definition of done
handles those those things beautifully
i think having you know in the case that
you mentioned it's really a ux ui
concern right it's this
user experience user interface stuff
guess what they're members of scrum
teams
right ux ui is a first class citizen in
scrum and so i think
really leaning into that idea as well
but i think i
right now i usually see teams leverage a
great definition of done to make sure
that they are staying consistent in the
areas where
there are some corporate standards and
things that need to be followed
so new realities are causing remote and
geographically dispersed teams to be
more prevalent
does that make it harder to ensure this
consistency
you know what i think teams can figure
that out now
i will say remote does make it more
difficult you know i just uh
had an article published over on silicon
republic
that the basically said look scrum
masters your job is now much much harder
right the the challenges of remote
amplify your challenge to
to help with individuals and
relationships and collaboration
and these organizational impediments
because they're going to be
hidden even deeper you know between zoom
calls and
and all these other things right and so
yes the job
that it becomes more difficult and we
take on
some some more complexity in this space
but i also believe
that truly cross-functional
self-organizing development teams
with strong product management product
ownership
and with a scrum master who is well
versed in facilitation
coaching mentoring teaching training all
the stances that we have to follow
they will find ways to sort this out
right i don't think these are impossible
challenges but i will say this
the nature of remote work amplifies the
impediments that currently exist in your
organization
and so it becomes even more crucial that
a scrum master has no tolerance for
these things and gets them out of the
way
because the impact is now 10x given the
remote nature of our work
thanks ryan so i want to talk now about
the key artifacts
let's start with the product backlog and
i'd like to understand your perspective
on ordering versus prioritizing items i
believe the scrum guide
focuses on the ordering yeah so this is
a hot topic
every class i teach we have to spend
quite a bit of time here because it is
such a
ingrained thing that we prioritize
things when it comes to product backlogs
if we use the pri the word priority
we're using the word priority wrong
and let me let me explain that i will
often get asked you know what are my
priorities
in my life and when i get asked that
question i'll say my family
right and then i get quiet and people
like well what's up what else right
i say well look if i say anything else
then i have invalidated my family as
being my priority
you cannot have two things as your as
your top priority right
there's only one thing there and so by
definition the word priority is singular
you can
if you once you say another thing that's
a priority you've invalidated that first
i
if i say family you know if i were to
say
whatever anything else after that i've
invalidated my family as a priority so
priority is a is not the right word to
use there
i would also say let's if we get past
the semantical argument so some people
will say you're being semantic that
doesn't matter well first of all words
are very important in culture
and so i would argue back that the words
we choose to use can change behavior
okay and so as a scrum master we're very
careful with words and so
with the word priority fine let's have
let's indulge this for a second
everything in my product backlog is
priority number one
which one should you do first now the
answer is usually
all of it right so this implies that
everything will be done on a product
backlog and everything is of equal
importance
neither of these things are true in
scrum there's no guarantees that a
product backlog item will be completed
and they are not all equal and so the
word priority causes some weird behavior
that we're trying to get away from
when we order something we are putting
an explicit order to the product backlog
this is
the most valuable thing this is the next
most valuable thing this is the next
most valuable thing
so on and so forth this this is an
expression of value
it shows us what are the most critical
things it also gives us opportunities to
make decisions about things lower on the
product backlog
that may or may not get done and so it
also shows us that there's some
uncertainty
and so we're trying to get the most
valuable things out first
right and then we're trying to figure
out if these lesser value things even
need to be done
and that leads to a different set of
behaviors right now we're being
empirical we're inspecting and adapting
we're a value we're driving off of value
not off of scope
you know it changes the way that we
think about things and so
short answer priority is not sufficient
right we need an order to the product
backlog to understand value
to understand the vision and to be able
to make trade-offs and decisions
uh because it is not certain that all
the work is going to get done
and not all of the work is equal does
that does that help
it does help and i also notice your book
that recommends having the product
backlog support
a short-term vision a midterm vision and
a long-term vision
and the short term i suppose corresponds
to the
minimal viable product yep how do you
get from
the midterm to the short term you know
what we have to be as a
the product owner job is very difficult
and i have a lot of
respect for the great product owners in
our community
they have to be ruthless right they have
to be
ruthless about what's valuable they have
to be ruthless about what's needed
look we use scrum as a as a risk
mitigation framework
and the sooner we can get something in
front of a customer the sooner we can
get
feedback now if it takes us 18 months to
get a minimally viable product out
we are at huge risk right we've got 18
months of investment and we're not sure
if this thing's important
now if we can just get down to one month
and showing a customer something
well we've just cut risk by quite a bit
right
and so i think it really comes down to
excellent product ownership is how we
get from that that bigger vision
to that mvp and realizing that uh
yeah the sooner we get something in
front of a customer the sooner we can
validate all of our assumptions
because keep in mind everything in your
product backlog is an assumption
you're assuming this is valuable it we
don't we can't validate
that the three v's right vision value
validation we don't
validate that what we did was valuable
until we get something in front of a
customer
and so the sooner we get in front of a
customer the sooner we can validate the
sooner we know
we're on the right path that we can the
more that we can protect our investment
all these great things flow so it's a
ruthless product owner laser focused on
value and validation that gets us there
what about exploratory work so sometimes
that is
needed so what should this ruthless
product wanna do in that case
time box it to something as small and as
meaningful as possible
right i think far too many this is this
will manifest as like a spike the dev
team will ask for a spike
we're unsure between two different
technologies and often i'll say you know
what take
take a sprint or two if i'm in a product
owner rule take one sprint build it both
ways and let's evaluate and go forward
if it's important enough right otherwise
i'll say look we have the
we have a sprint to make a decision you
know what does that experiment look like
but we time box it and we have
and we basically say look there's a time
box to this uh
the spike to this exploratory work and
there's an outcome we're after
either we're trying to make a decision
we're trying to learn about a technology
but we have a defined outcome of success
for this experiment
or a way to refute the experiment and we
time box it
very strictly makes sense there's also
you know a lot of discussion i hear
about the size of a backlog
i know there's a lot of discussion of
that in your book as well
and the goal is not to get it too large
but how do you prevent that
well it it's funny like i i do this
keynote all over the world for
especially at scrum or i used to when i
used to travel now we don't travel
anymore right
but one of the questions i'll ask is all
right who in the audience has a product
backlog and all the hands go up in the
air and everyone's all excited yeah we
get to participate too and
and it's a fun little aspect of the talk
then i'll say that's really cool i'm
glad we all have product backlogs how
many of you have a product backlog
item on your product backlog that's
older than three months and everyone
laughs and their hands stay up
i say all right how about older than six
months and everyone gets kind of nervous
because
oh he's gonna keep adding and so now
it's it's a year
two years three years four the record's
nine years
and so i actually stopped the keynote um
had the lights brought up
got this person a microphone and and
just i was like
man what is it that's nine years old on
a product backlog
and turns out it was a it was financial
industry
it was a mainframe change on a backend
system
and the guy was adamant it's like no
ryan we have to make this change i'm
like sir it's been nine years
and you're still doing great and it was
like a light bulb moment for him
right it was this idea that oh i can let
this go that things will be okay
i think that's the first step for a
product owner right
if it's been nine years and your company
is still running and you're still
profitable and things are going you can
probably get rid of that product backlog
item i think you'll be
all right but i also think it's
important to understand that
as a product owner i can't keep track of
a thousand things
meaningfully right neither can your dev
team and in fact it stresses
everybody out and so when it when todd
and i go into work with companies one of
the first things we'll say is look
anything older than six months on your
product backlog cut it
and people freak out and six months is
arbitrary maybe it's three months maybe
it's 12 months
pick a line draw that line and cut
everything beneath that line
and when we do that people get really
freaked out let's put it on a secret
spreadsheet
let's say just cut it because we promise
you here's the second thing that'll help
a product owner right the second insight
if it's truly important if the thing
that we cut is just
massively important it will come back
through feedback from your customers
i promise it'll come back if it's
important so let go of this idea that
every idea is important
let go of this idea of having to have
the this massive inventory of work
focus on again leverage a scrum value
the the scrum value of focus
figure out what's truly important cut
the rest if you cut a little too deep
your customers will tell you and that
idea will come back
i think if they can embrace that idea
and really believe it it becomes a lot
easier
to to shrink the size of these these
wildly overgrown product backlogs
so episode 389 might be interesting i'll
put a link to that in the show notes
it discusses what basecamp calls a shape
up method
so they certainly believe having a
backlog is a
problem and they also believe that scrum
pushes too many strategic decisions down
so they recommend more time-boxed
projects and more upfront definitions uh
before the team
gets involved with that so it might be
interesting to check that out for our
listeners i'll put that in
let's talk about the sprint backlog now
sure what is it
is that a forecast or a commitment
sprint backlog is a forecast
right these are the things that we think
we could achieve during a sprint
we're not committing to them we believe
that one
or many of the things on the sprint
backlog will help us achieve the sprint
goal
which is where our commitment lies so
the sprint backlog is definitely a
forecast
so it's a forecast so what is the
inspection needed as the sprint
progresses to make sure that
it is in the right direction well every
day during a daily scrum
we're going to take the an opportunity
to see whether or not
we're making progress towards our sprint
goal and we're going to take a look at
our sprint backlog and see
what have we learned about this work so
far what kind of updates do we need to
make so
when we're inspecting our progress
towards the sprint goal that sprint
backlog is front and center
we may have to make some adaptations
based on some things we've learned
by it's again it is through doing the
work that we learn about the work we
need to do
which is why we meet every day in a
daily scrum to update our sprint backlog
to
track to track our progress towards a
sprint goal to collaboratively
build a plan about how we're going to
work together over the next 48 hours
and so we're continually inspecting the
work because we're in a complex domain
and we're learning about the work
constantly right
so if we knew everything up front we'd
just go do the work we'd just build it
right but we don't and so we're learning
discovering experimenting
and that sprint backlog is an expression
of all that learning during a sprint
and we're updating it continually we're
we're keeping the work and the
the stage in our progress transparent
and up-to-date
so we have to inspect and adapt
frequently because we're constantly
learning about the things we're building
does that make sense yes but when you
say we
you mean the dev team i'm yes good call
good
good follow-up yes i definitely mean the
dev team
with some product owner insights mixed
in as well
what about the scrum master you know
what it's not my job as a scrum master
to keep the sprint
backlog up to date and it's not my job
to build a burn down chart
it's not my job to babysit the dev team
and so
here's the deal we make in scrum if the
development team agrees to keep their
progress
visible and transparent we agree not to
pull them into constant status meetings
right and so that's the deal if they
choose not to do that then as a scrum
master i can't stop
a manager or a director from saying all
right come to this status meeting i
don't know where we're at
and so as a scrum master that's not my
job to manage their progress
and i'm i'm typically i'm not involved
in that as if
as long as i can manage that to happen
right so
we are inspecting the team's inspecting
and now they have to deal with the
situation that the work is actually much
larger than they
thought what do they do so that's a
that's a great moment
to pull the product owner into a
discussion
right so the dev team and the product
owner they have a highly collaborative
relationship
these these two groups have to get along
very well
so first of all i'm very proud of this
dev team right so they they've found an
issue they realize the work is too big
and immediately they go to their product
owner and they say look
what we thought was possible is turning
out to be a lot
bigger so now we need to decide how do
we cut things how do we change things
how do we reshape
the scope of our sprint which is really
the sprint backlog right it's a forecast
of scope
how do we reshape this so that we can
still achieve our sprint goal
right that might mean we're going to cut
two or three things from the sprint
backlog
but we're going to make sure that that
sprint goal is still achieved so we
we always protect the sprint goal but
the forecast of work can change
based on what we learn but it's that
it's going to be a collaborative
decision
and discussion with the product owner in
the dev team but ultimately
the dev team owns the sprint backlog and
so they can make changes as they see fit
but they are committed to achieving the
sprint goal
that was discussed during sprint
planning and agreed to by the scrum team
does that help yes that helps what about
bugs should they be treated differently
than features
they're just another product backlog
item and it's up to the discretion of a
product owner to decide whether or not a
bug
goes above or below a feature at any
given point
now let me let me caveat that with you
know because
i'm sure there's some listeners who are
like well wait a minute what about if
production's down
the answer is yeah we solved that right
i i'd imagine
i can't i can't think of a product owner
on the planet who would say no
ignore the fact that prods down i need
this new feature so i'm not talking
about that
i'm talking about the system's working
things are happening but there's some
behavior we don't expect like that's
what that's kind of the scope for a bug
does that make sense yes okay so
keep your eye on this sprint goal and
yes collaborate with the product owner
to to see how best to get to that
that's kind of your recommendation it's
it's that's just professional scrum
right that sprint goal gives us focus
right and it's our it's what we commit
to so it's focus and commitment
and so we have to be open to
shifting scope changing scope in order
to maintain
focus and do it to maintain that
commitment
i it's just that's professional scrum
and that's how we
we act transparently that's how we
that's how we preserve delivery
is just by by following that path
let's talk about the scrum activities
for a little bit
sure the daily scrum so what is the
scrum masters
role in the daily scrum totally optional
actually
so the scrum master doesn't even have to
attend i think early on while the dev
team's learning how to best use the the
daily scrum to their
to their maximum advantage it's very
helpful to have a scrub master
facilitate it but quite honestly as a
scrum master my job is just to make sure
it happens
and nothing more and we did talk about
the team
ensuring that they are progressing to
the
sprint goal that's a key focus of the
team in
the daily scrum um what about sprints
and before we get to sprints
you know there are these terms use done
and then there's done done
what is the difference yeah dunn refers
to the definition of done
and when i was a developer i would use
this i used to say yeah something's done
and
but what i meant was that it was running
locally what the project manager heard
was that it was deployed somewhere and
and chaos would ensue right because what
you know when i said i didn't say done
done
i just said done and and so in scrum we
have this definition of done it's a
whole team it's a whole it's an
organizational understanding
of what it means to be potentially
releasable so when i say
this product backlog item is done what
i'm saying is
it could go in front of a customer right
and that definition of done defines
all the things it makes everything that
would have to happen for that to be true
for this pbi to be potentially
releasable for this product whichever
level you're
thinking for this thing to be
potentially releasable
here's everything that has to be true
and it's not just
tech stuff sometimes it's the marketing
plan is complete or the website is
updated or the train
training videos are done or customer
communication has occurred
uh legal and compliance have signed off
um there's all sorts of things that go
into this definition of done
that have absolutely nothing to do with
writing code
or creating product but are essential
to the organization right so what's
interesting is it just makes it
transparent
all the moving parts to ship something
and it really helps us avoid you know
the you know one of the worst things i
ever did in my career as a developer
was when someone came to me and said can
you just make this one little change
quickly and i said yes
ignoring like all of the things that you
know needed to be done because i didn't
know about all of them and
it led to chaos this stops that when
someone says can we just do this one
little change the answer is heck no look
at this list of things that have to
happen before we can say
done now go talk to our product owner
quit hassling me about this and
but yeah done means potentially
releasable done is a
is a is a look at completeness and it
just makes that transparent for
everybody it gets rid of done done
i've even seen companies where dun dun
dun
was where you could finally go to
production we've wiped all that nonsense
out
definition of done is just such a
powerful tool for understanding what
completeness actually means
so what about the sprint review though
if it's you know the feature is complete
but
all these other activities like
documentation marketing etc are not
done should the future be demoed
uh no we should never show undone work
in a sprint review
right so professional professionals do
not show
undone work so we can have a
conversation about it
and we can talk to our stakeholders
about all the things that we did but
we do not if we were to show a
stakeholder something that was undone
even though we can say a thousand times
this is not ready
they might leave with the wrong
impression right it could lead to
misinformation and besides the the
sprint review
it's far more than just uh a demo
anyways like
this is an opportunity to to meet with
customers users stakeholders
this event is designed to to get rich
feedback about how the products doing in
the marketplace
updates about budgets uh all with the
the intention the actual outcome of a
of a professional sprint review is an
updated product backlog
with the latest and greatest information
about our product and so
the demo part is such a small part of it
anyways but in this case
you know to directly answer what you've
asked no
you do not show that work you do not
claim it as done you don't even
let someone leave with the
misrepresentation or misperception that
it is done
it waits till the next sprint or
whenever you actually whenever you
actually meet that definition of done
it's a pretty strict stance isn't it
that's exactly what i was thinking and i
was wondering though doesn't it go
against the need to get
feedback early from the stakeholders you
know what we are holding
a high bar of professionalism on scrum
teams right so i
i do not teach certified scrum class i
don't we are teaching professional scrum
and so when we say we do not show undone
work we do not show work that doesn't
meet the definition of done we mean it
and we so what we need to figure out is
why
didn't we get there like and so that's
you know sprint retrospective is the
event after the review
what improvements do we need to make so
that when we get to
the end of a sprint we have something to
get feedback on because you're right
it's
not a good thing uh to delay feedback i
mean we've talked about that the sooner
you get feedback the less risk you have
the sooner you know that you're on track
but if we start blurring those lines
if we start telling teams it's okay to
show undone work
how long before it's okay to deploy
undone work how long be
how many lines do we cross there right
so a professional scrum team
does not show a work that does not meet
the definition of done
so i think you know besides leadership
buying which you mentioned was an
important prereq
um what i take away from this is coming
up with a
definition of done is another important
prereq
i so i i definitely think you need it
during that you need to have a
definition of done ready during that
first sprint definitely
yes i i could even go along with the
pre-wreck i agree with you
it's important like it's people ask me
they say ryan scrum is so
big and and in a sense it is where
should we start and i do not recommend
doing all of it at once
please please please do not use
waterfall to implement scrum
but i think a great starting point is
the definition of done
define done at an organizational and
team level
and just doing that alone will change
behavior almost instantly
it has to so demoing is a small part of
scrum but it is a par
important part and you know there's
talking you know just explaining what
was done getting more feedback etc and
we did talk earlier about the scrum
master
initially being a bridge but over time
that bridge should get smaller and
smaller
and the team should do the talking so
is can you talk more about that like who
should demo
you know you don't want everybody
demoing or do you
so when when there is a demo component
to a sprint review
i so i've seen it done many different
ways the one person i would say who
should not
do that is the scrub master i
the scrum master is facilitating they're
there to make sure the event happens
that it's a
that's moving in a a positive direction
but they are not the center of attention
right one of the hardest parts about the
scrum master role is that none of it's
about you
right it is about everyone else and it's
really hard especially when you come
from a leadership
a project manager that kind of
background to really deprogram that it
takes a long time to sync that in but
you know to your question directly like
who who's really
doing these different things i would
rather the dev team if we are going to
show work that the dev team
runs that if we're going to talk about
budgets and progress
that the product owner is running that
if we're collecting feedback or engaging
with you know stakeholder
i'd really love to see the product owner
in the mix of that
and so i think the people accountable
for that work should be the ones
actually responsible for showing that
work and
so yeah i think the dev team can demo
their own stuff they don't need someone
speaking for them and the product owner
can
can manage their stakeholders and you
know what though
i love seeing here's like a tip that
probably did not it did not make it in
the book
uh when i see a product owner deferring
to a dev team member to answer a
question for a stakeholder that's a
really good signal
that the relationship's going well and
that the product owner trusts the dev
team and that the dev team has shown
that they're
that they're professionals and so i i'm
looking for those little things as well
but
yeah the people closest to the work
should be the ones talking about
and showcasing and demoing and
discussing the work
so ryan i think your answer to my next
question is going to be
follow the framework but i'll ask it
anyway what happens if
the organization does everything else
but doesn't hold retrospectives
what is the impact they never improve
that's tragic right continuous
improvement is essential for
for agile practices and for a scrum
implementation
if we skip the retro i mean we never sit
down and figure out how we could get
better
it's almost like we're wasting the whole
investment you know
that would be tragic that would oh
that's a bummer follow the framework
your answer is right okay
let's start to wrap up but i'd like to
ask you first is there any critical
topic
that might be covered in your book or
you want to talk about that we did not
cover today
you know there's a chapter in the book
that's in fixing your scrum that todd
and i
struggled with and we the it's the one
you know he and i are pretty we're very
aligned in our views on scrum and
professionalism
but there's a chapter in there there's a
management chapter
working with management respecting
management and we really struggle
because it should not be in the book
right it's not but what we found was
scrum masters have had so much trouble
relating to management like my
background is in management like i
worked through the fortune 500
up the leadership chain like i've worked
in the role
and i was always frustrated with the way
scrum masters would try to talk at me
or try to tell me that i was wrong or
that and so we
we decided you know what there's a
chapter in there about
working productively and positively with
management and leadership
trying to meet the needs that they're
expressing but in a way that still
honors the values and principles of
scrum
and i think that chapter it's the one
chapter that's generated the most emails
i think
positive and negative so some people do
not like the fact that we're holding the
scrum master accountable for bad
relationships with leadership
but if you're not fulfilling that role
or if you're not fulfilling that service
level it is kind of your fault but i
think that's a chapter to focus on it i
think it's just so important to
understand that our service to the
organization is essential
to our scrum team success and the better
relationship we have with management and
leadership
the faster we can get impediments
removed and if we approach them in
positive productive ways like if we
partner with leadership and management
instead of turning them into the enemy
we can get a lot more done
and i think that's a that's a chapter
that every scrum master should
definitely read
awesome what is the goal of your podcast
agile for humans
you know what it started as uh there's a
group of us who would get together and
just
talk and so esther derby don gray
you know george dinwiddie woody zuul i
mean just uh
i have no idea why i was ever on any of
those calls like
i did not deserve a space there but
fortunately they let me join in
and one day don and i were talking and
it was actually don gray's idea
he said you know ryan you should record
these and
i was like all right but i mean not even
my mom would listen to this and so
why would we post it but we posted it
and like
300 people listened to it within like i
don't know five or six hours
and we thought whoa wait a minute that's
kind of interesting and so what the goal
really is
like we just want to get people together
and have meaningful conversations
about aspects of agile without the tools
and the big mechanisms and the big
corporate all this stuff
like agile for humans it sounds like a
weird title but it's really saying look
this is for human stuff
right we all have baggage and we're all
wired differently and we're all these
flawed human
beings and and we're trying to honor and
respect that and make sure that the
conversations around
agile are focused on the people and the
interactions and the collaboration and
not whether or not jira can do a certain
thing or
whether or not rally is the right tool
or you know just it's about
people and we want to just have that
human-centric attitude towards the
things we do and
and hopefully the show achieves that
right it's just real raw
direct conversation and so far i think
people have kind of liked it so
hopefully we get that across i don't
know we'll put a link to your podcast
and your book in the show notes
thank you how can people contact you
ryan ripley.com is probably the easiest
at ryan ripley on twitter
ryan at ryanripley.com for email i'll
tell you this though if you reach out
and contact me i promise to answer
so that's either like a good thing or
it's kind of like a curse or a threat
i'm not sure which so
but if you reach out i'm happy to
discuss any of these items
the book um you know what if you do pick
up the book and if you
i'd love to hear what you think good or
bad twitter is probably the best at ryan
ripley but yeah please give us your
feedback
todd and i are we love hearing whether
or not you know what worked what didn't
uh whether or not people are using
pieces of the book to their advantage
you know if it's helping all that stuff
is just wonderful so yeah please reach
out
thank you ryan thanks all for listening
and thanks ryan for being on the show
thanks for having me this was a ton of
fun really some of the better questions
we've gotten about this so thank you so
much it was uh
i had to think a few times there and uh
so really enjoyed it like i
i don't know if you can tell i could
probably geek out on this stuff and talk
about it all day so really appreciate
this opportunity
appreciate that bye everyone developers
take your marks
it's time to upgrade your data platform
to inner systems iris
it's time to deliver complex mission
critical applications in the fastest
route possible
it's time to use any data from any
source it's time to embed analytics and
create interactive user interfaces
so what are you waiting for choose your
language choose your tools
choose your environment collaborate
build faster
and deploy more efficiently done and
done tomorrow's next breakthroughs are
waiting for you today
intersystems iris data platform the
fastest way to build applications
ready set code
start coding for free visit
intersystems.com
try to try iris
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at
se radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening